So I'm glad you were able to go today. Yeah, it was
great that we had that field trip yesterday to go look at
the עירוב. eruv. All right, so we're going to
start, and today's דף daf is דף צ, Daf Tzadi, and we
pick up at the bottom of פט עמוד ב, Peh Tet Amud
Bet, and the focus is this issue about even without this עירוב,
eruv, again, places are רשות היחיד reshus hayachid that's surrounded with walls,
but without an עירוב, eruv, what's considered one domain as opposed to
distinct domains. And the גמרא Gemara has been dealing with the position
of the חכמים Chachamim that say that the rooftops are considered to
be distinct domains because the homes below are distinct ownership and
therefore the rooftops would need an עירוב, eruv, but the גמרא Gemara
said that if you did something to establish a more serious presence
like that you're dwelling on one of the rooftops, then that more
dominates the others, the others don't have anybody really dwelling on it
and then you're actually allowed to have access to the others. So
that one example was when you made a fixed ladder or you
built real walls on it and with that we pick up and
the גמרא Gemara says like this, four lines from the bottom.
אמר אביי בנה עלייה על גבי ביתו ועשה לפניה דקה ארבע, Amar
Abaye bana aliyah al gabei beiso ve'asah lefaneha daka arba, if you
made a second story on your house, you basically, you know, turn
your roof
into a second story. So you've like we said before, you exactly,
you know, you really are living on your roof, so as we
said yesterday that should give you therefore,
you know, be access to the other rooftops.
So but ועשה לפניה דקה ארבע, ve'asah lefaneha daka arba, you made
a דקה daka four. Now דקה, daka, what exactly a דקה daka
is, in the past if you might remember, it meant a little
barrier.
Here רש״י Rashi chooses to explain that it means an opening. תוספות
Tosafot tries to fit it in with the old explanation that means
a barrier, but רש״י Rashi says that it means you made a
little doorway.
הותרה בכל הגגין כולן, hutrah bechol hagagin kulan, you're allowed to have
access to
all of the rooftops for this reason. The door opens up onto
the other rooftops, so you basically have made have turned
a apology, you have your marker?
You're the only one who did this, right?
I left my marker downstairs.
No, you're the only one who did it, right?
You're the only one who did it.
Sure, if other people did it, then you have competing room then
you have competing buildings above. But basically, you made a second story.
Now the second story didn't necessarily have access to the roofs, right?
Because what happened was we're going to get a marker here. Thank
you, our savior. Okay, so you basically have all of these places
across these roofs, right? There's these roofs and people don't really live
there, but because they sort of quasi-live there, that gives, you know,
that according to the חכמים Chachamim make them considered distinct, right? Remember,
according to רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir and רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon since
that's quasi. Okay, anyway, because according to רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir and
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon since nobody really lives there, they're not considered
distinct. But according to the חכמים Chachamim because this is A and
this is B and this is, you know,
quasi-B, okay, that makes them pseudo-distinct. But if you turned this into
a real living there, then these don't consider they're not distinct vis-a-vis
what it means to seriously live there. So what you did is
you went ahead and you built a second story. So now you're
really living here. Okay, and he says if you make a דקה
daka which רש״י Rashi says means a door and now you have
access, because you could have a second story that you get in
up through, you know, up inside the building without actually getting onto
the roof. But now you actually have a door that gives you
access, so these are not considered distinct from a real person from
a real living there. Okay, so that's consistent with what we said
yesterday. And you can carry there? Yeah, that's what it means. And
because you have it's all a רשות היחיד reshus hayachid and you
can carry, yeah, it's all the same because it's all right, they're
not considered and the interesting question is which is not stated in
the גמרא Gemara is is that then can other people carry there
as well, you know, because if A is it's like you don't
really own these the point is that with a real dwelling there
the
quasi-presence the sometime presence of other people pales in significance so then
maybe everybody should be allowed to, right? It shouldn't be that only
limited to A, it removes any distinctiveness from the domains.
Yeah and you're relying on a לחי lechi and קורה korah like
done to the חצר chatzer because, like you know, because yeah
well these are houses anyway they have four walls, so you don't
need a לחי lechi or קורה. korah.
No, for the whole area of the rooftop?
Yeah the area rooftop all have four walls because they're all all
the tops of buildings that have four walls. You don't need so
you're
saying you don't even need a לחי lechi and קורה? korah?
Right. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like
this, אמר רבא פעמים שהדקה לאיסור, Amar Rava pe'amim shehadaka le'issur, sometimes
this again רש״י Rashi we just this doorway can create a problem
and רש״י Rashi says even according to רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon who
naturally says that all the rooftops are one domain, how can this
create a problem or רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, excuse me, that says
all the rooftops are one domain. היכי דמי דעביד להו להני טויאתא,
Heichi dami de'avid lehu lehani tavita, you make it near like a
garden. of your house. דאמרי De'amri לנטורי טביתא הוא דעבידא, linturei tavita
hu da'avida,
you're doing it to watch your garden. So basically, again, I'm not
exactly sure of the configuration, but somehow you make your door here,
on this side, and it overlooks like a garden area, I don't
know, maybe you got a ladder going down or something like that,
okay? So according to that, even though רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon normally
says, look, all rooftops are one thing, because you have sort of
made this rooftop to serve the area below, you have defined it
sort of not in the same category as these other rooftops. All
right, I can't say I fully understand that, but that's what the
story is. Let's move on. בעי רמי בר חמא. Ba'ei Rami bar
Chama. So Rabbi bar Chama asked, top of צ"א ע"ב. Tzadi Alef
Amud Bet. שתי אמות בגג ושתי אמות בעמוד מהו? Shtei amot bagag
u'shtei amot ba'amud mahu? So this is working within Rava's position, if
you remember yesterday, excuse me, Rav's position, that Rav said that you
when you have all of these rooftops, okay, we'll go back to
the normal case, you've got all of these rooftops, and this is
according to the רבנן Rabbanan that say that each one of them
is distinct. You cannot go from A to B. And the question
is can you go four אמות amot within A? Is it, remember
the phrase, פרוץ במילואו למקום האסור לו?
parutz bimilo'o
lemakom ha'assur lo? Okay, does the fact that you have might have
a virtual wall going up, enough to say it's distinct from B,
that at least you can carry within A itself, or since according
to the חכמים Chachamim you can't go from A to B, you
also can't carry within A more than four אמות. amot. So he
is assuming like the latter, like the position of רב, Rav, that
you cannot carry within A more than four אמות. amot. And now
the question he wants to know is, let's say right near the
roof of A, you've got a little platform, okay, this isn't a
house, it's a platform, I don't know how to show that it's
not a house, but okay, you've got a little platform. Can you
go ahead and move something from here to here? And even if
it's within four אמות. amot. Okay, so the question is that is
this, the bottom line of the question is you're not going more
than four אמות, amot, that's fine, but I want to know that
is this considered to be a distinct רשות? reshut? Because remember, you
can't go from A to B even less than four אמות, amot,
because that's going into a different רשות. reshut. What is the story
about a place that doesn't have a different person living in it,
like the B, like the B case, but is not a rooftop?
It's a platform. Is that considered a different רשות reshut or not?
Can you go from A to the platform?
Okay, well, yes, based on everything we said about roofs being different
from other things, right, so let's take a look. That's what certainly
stands to reason. So let's see what the גמרא Gemara says. שתי
אמות בגג ושתי אמות בעמוד מהו? Shtei amot bagag u'shtei amot ba'amud
mahu? What's the story? So
אמר רבא מאי קמיבעיא ליה? Amar Rava mai kamibaya lei? What type
of question is that?
כרמלית ורשות היחיד קמיבעיא ליה? Karmelit u'reshut hayachid kamibaya lei? How could
you even think you could do it? One is a כרמלית, karmelit,
one is a רשות היחיד. reshut hayachid. Now, which is which? רש"י
Rashi says, so
רש"י Rashi says the עמוד amud is the רשות היחיד reshut hayachid
and we're talking
that it is, where was, what happened to my pen? I just
lost it.
It's on the floor?
Yeah,
I just saw it a second ago. Oh, there it is.
It's hidden very well, camouflage. Anyway, רש"י Rashi says we're talking about
it's ten by four, this is a רשות היחיד. reshut hayachid. So
why are we calling this a כרמלית? karmelit? So רש"י Rashi says
because it doesn't have one of the major qualities of רשות היחיד.
reshut hayachid. What what doesn't what do you not what does it
not have? You can't carry, well it has walls, it has virtual
walls, but the same way this has virtual, but you can't carry
in it, right? Because of this problem of the exposed to B.
So it's like an effective כרמלית karmelit
because it doesn't, you're not able to carry in it the same
way you can in רשות היחיד. reshut hayachid. So of course they're
distinct. Besides the fact that this is a roof and that isn't
a roof or whatever, but of course they're distinct. This is a
כרמלית karmelit and that's רשות היחיד, reshut hayachid, a quote-unquote כרמלית, karmelit,
you can't carry in it. That's the way רש"י Rashi understands. תוספות
Tosafot says the opposite. This is a רשות היחיד reshut hayachid and
we're talking that the עמוד amud is, you know, is less than
ten טפחים tefachim high. So the עמוד amud is a כרמלית. karmelit.
But let's deal with רש"י, Rashi, okay? This is not a normal
רשות היחיד, reshut hayachid, so of course it is distinct from the
pillar which is a normal רשות היחיד. reshut hayachid. So what type
of a question was that? Of course they're distinct. So let's see
what the גמרא's Gemara answer is. So
אלא Ela says the גמרא, Gemara, I'm sorry. ורמי בר חמא אגב
חורפיה לא עיין בה. VeRami bar Chama agav churpeih lo iyein bah.
Because רמי בר חמא, Rami bar Chama, he was so sharp, he
didn't, you know, sometimes he didn't slow down enough to think it
through. Some people are like that. They have a really sharp question.
Whoa, wait, slow down, like just process for a minute. Okay, so
the first thing the גמרא Gemara said was it was like, okay,
you're right, it wasn't a good question, the answer is obvious. But
then the גמרא Gemara says אלא הכי קמיבעיא ליה, ela hachi kamibaya
lei, this must have been his question. Now before we even see
the גמרא's Gemara rephrasing, I find this extremely like an insightful window,
you know, because some very often the גמרא Gemara challenges a question,
says okay, this is really what he asked. And the question always
is like does the גמרא Gemara really think that's what he really
asked, or is the גמרא Gemara like trying to say like here's
what he should have asked, or you know, here's like a sympathetic
read even though we don't really believe that he asked this, but
it's the only way the question makes sense, so we're going to
sort of, you know, act as if this is the question that
was asked. So it seems like that's what the גמרא Gemara is
saying here. First it says, yeah you're right, רמי בר חמא Rami
Bar Chama rushed to ask this question, and he and actually he
missed, you know, he didn't ask the question properly. And then it
says, okay here's what he asked. So what is it? Did he
really ask thing B or did he ask A and he was,
you know, and he misspoke? So it sounds like he says, you
know, if you it's more like of a virtual statement. If you
were going to ask something, this is what he should have asked.
Okay, right, or this is what he meant to
ask. Right, or this is what he, oh I see, so the
לא עיין בה lo ayen bah is that he didn't he didn't
slow down enough to articulate correctly. Maybe. Okay, anyway. So this is
what really he meant to ask. אלא הכי קמיבעיא ליה. Ella hachi
kamibaia lei. בין אמות בגג ובין אמות באכסדרה מהו. Bein amot begag
u-bein amot be-achsadra mahu. Let's say you have a not a a
normal not a normal what do you call it, not a normal
עמוד amud there, but what you actually have is you have a
portico. You've got another roof, but it's not a roof of a
בית, bayit, it's a roof of, it's like a portico. And same
thing, is that considered different? We're keeping within ארבע אמות, arba amot,
is it considered different? So this is a, you know, is this
technically a רשות היחיד reshut hayachid but it's quote-unquote a כרמלית? karmelit?
Okay. This is also technically a רשות היחיד reshut hayachid because we
will assume, although it's a little bit of a question, but somehow
we'll assume that you got either the edge of the roof or
something, you know, is considered to be enough of a wall. Okay.
Is it also a כרמלית? karmelit? So, so it could be does
it also have the quasi-כרמלית karmelit status? So the answer is possibly
yes for one of two reasons. Either רש"י Rashi gives two scenarios.
One is is that it's a huge space and it's over בית
סאתים. beit satayim. Remember right that's huge. And if you remember בית
סאתים beit satayim דלא הוקף לדירה delo hukaf ledira that isn't made
for inhabitant is a כרמלית. karmelit. But the other scenario that רש"י
Rashi says is actually an easier one. רש"י Rashi actually says it
doesn't really try let me just double check רש"י Rashi make sure
I'm saying it right.
Right. The other scenario רש"י Rashi says is is that no, it
doesn't have walls. There's nothing that you can count as a wall.
So it's not even
a real רשות היחיד reshut hayachid and a pseudo-כרמלית, karmelit, it's not
a רשות היחיד reshut hayachid at all, it's just a כרמלית. karmelit.
Okay? Because it doesn't have walls, it's a portico, it's got a
roof, doesn't have walls.
Or doesn't have enough walls.
Or whatever, but yeah, but presumably it's open on all sides. So
can you go from a pseudo-כרמלית karmelit to a כרמלית? karmelit? On
the one hand they're both effectively a כרמלית, karmelit, but this is
really רשות היחיד. reshut hayachid. And on the other hand also this
has people living in it and that doesn't have people living in
it. So even though it's only pseudo-present up here, you know, it's
enough to make these considered distinct from one another, so maybe that
also should say that it's distinct from a place that nobody lives
in and that should be and therefore it's an issue. So let's
take a look at how the גמרא Gemara frames it. Okay. אלא
בין אמות בגג ובין אמות באכסדרה
מהו.
Ella bein amot
begag u-bein amot be-achsadra mahu. מי אמרינן כיון דהאי חזי לדירה והאי
לא
חזי לדירה. mi amrinan keivan dehai chazi ledira vehai lo chazi ledira.
In reality nobody lives on the roof of A and nobody lives
on the roof of B. The only reason we're saying A is
somewhat distinct from B is because people live below, but in reality
nobody really lives on the roof of A. So חדא רשותא היא.
chada reshuta hi. They're both effectively the same. Okay. And and the
benefit of this is is that here it's a different person that
lives in B. Nobody lives here. So since this isn't a real
place of habitation and this isn't and this isn't a different person
than here, maybe it should be considered acceptable and okay, and it's
better than roof B. Okay. Is that what we say?
או דילמא, o dilma, or do we say, כיון דמיגג לגג אסר
מיגג לאכסדרה
נמי
אסר? keivan demigag legag assar migag le'achsadra nami assar? It's too close
for comfort. You know, experientially it feels like going from A to
B, he's going from A to the roof of the אכסדרה. achsadra.
And for that reason it is going to be it is going
to be a problem, even though even though technically it is not
a different domain. It's not different in that you live more on
A than B, you don't really live on A. And it's not
a problem that it's not a different ownership. But nevertheless it's similar
enough to going from A to B that we're going to say
that it's forbidden. Okay. So that's the question. Of course more more
troubling is you're going from something that's a genuine רשות היחיד reshut
hayachid to something that's a real כרמלית, karmelit, assuming it doesn't have
walls. And that just by itself should be problem. So that's why
רש"י Rashi gives the other explanation that it actually does have walls
or enough walls, but it's huge, it's more than בית סאתים. beit
satayim. So it's again something that's really a רשות היחיד reshut hayachid
and and like virtually, you know, pseudo-a כרמלית karmelit
and that would make them very similar. And then the only reason
not to go from one to the other is because it's so
similar as going from A to B. Okay. So that's that question.
Yes, but does somebody live in A? What if it's like vacant?
The house?
Yeah.
So that would change things because that's like you know somebody doesn't
live in a house in a חצר chatzer and they don't create
a problem for the rest of the people in the חצר. chatzer.
So you're right and this is assuming an actual presence in a
house. Okay, so that's that question. בעי, be'ei, the whole today's דף
daf is going to be questions like this. So,
right. Not really. Okay. בעי רב ביבי בר אביי Ba'ei Rav Bibi
bar Abaye or רב ביבי בר אביי. Rav Bibi bar Abayis. בעי
רב ביבי בר אביי, Ba'ei Rav Bibi bar Abaye, בית שבגגו ובית
שבחורבה מה? Bayis she-begago u-vayis she-bachurvah mah? Let's say this is not
an אכסדרה achsadra which is very similar to the גג, gag, let's
say this is actually just an empty lot. Okay, you've got just
an empty lot here. I don't know if that makes it better.
Anyway. Okay. Fine. So, and you somehow want to just go from
here into there, from one רשות היחיד reshus ha-yachid to another, are
you allowed to do it? Now that is very different, right? I
mean, it's just not like the same type of thing, it's not
raised off the ground, it's not a roof. תוספות Tosafot says maybe
it's a roof in the חורבה, churvah, but רש"י Rashi says it's
not even a roof, okay? And, you know, and it certainly raises
the question which we haven't addressed yet, which is: can you go
according to the חכמים Chachamim from a roof to actually to the
yard, right? Or from a roof to a house?
Because is the reason that they say that you cannot go from
here to here because there are distinct owners? But here what's similar
is גג gag and גג gag is similar, right? But A and
B is different, and therefore it's a problem. What happens if you
had another scenario where you had, you know, where you had גג
gag versus חצר, chatzer, but you had A and here nobody was
there, it was an empty חצר. chatzer. Okay, so this isn't a
problem, there's no different owners. Would they have a problem from the
fact that you're going from a גג gag to a חצר? chatzer?
Is that by itself a problem? Okay, so that's not clear according
to the חכמים. Chachamim. Am I confusing everybody sufficiently? You might remember
according to רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir said you
can go from any גג gag to another one. But he didn't
necessarily say you can go from a גג gag to a חצר.
chatzer. Maybe the fact that it's different, גג gag versus חצר. chatzer.
The חכמים Chachamim are saying that's not enough, because this is different.
What's not clear is what if this isn't a problem, but there's
a difference from גג gag to חצר chatzer according to the חכמים.
Chachamim. Anyway, I think I've successfully confused you. But the question here
is, that is similar to this question. Can you go from here,
right, can you go into a חורבה? churvah? What is the story?
So let's take a look at what the גמרא Gemara says.
Okay.
Now רש"י Rashi says, right. Now רש"י Rashi actually says, I'm sorry,
the point that I forgot to make was, as we've emphasized this
status of a כרמלית, karmelis, רש"י Rashi says that this חורבה churvah
might have walls here, but one side is open to a רשות
הרבים. reshus ha-rabim. So the status of this חורבה churvah is a
כרמלית karmelis as well. So again, you're going from כרמלית karmelis to
a כרמלית, karmelis, okay, but it's not the same experience as גג
gag to גג. gag. The rooftop of the אכסדרה achsadra we said
might have been too close of גג gag to גג, gag, what's
the story about the גג gag to the חורבה? churvah? It's again
כרמלית karmelis or pseudo-כרמלית karmelis or to כרמלית, karmelis, is that okay
or not? Or maybe it's not okay because even though you won't
confuse it with this case, but it's too big of a difference
just going from a גג gag to a חורבה. churvah. That in
itself is too big of a difference.
Yes. Stay on top and look and watch over your guard. So
if you can't do that, why would you be allowed to go
down?
That was when, no, that wasn't, that was when your whole rooftop
was designated as essentially a non-rooftop, it was there for the guarding.
And therefore that made it according to, according to...
what's that mean it was there for the guard?
I don't know. I'm going to bracket that question. This is just
confusing enough. But that was not according to the חכמים. Chachamim. That
was according to רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir that said basically all the
roofs are the same, but if you turn your roof into a
garden overlook you've taken it out of the group of the other
roofs. That wasn't the point, that wasn't the scenario here. We're dealing
with חכמים Chachamim that say all the roofs are different because of
different ownership. But how about going not to a differently owned roof,
how about going to a חורבה? churvah? So that let's see what
the גמרא Gemara does with this... or חצר... chatzer... but the גמרא's
Gemara question was a חורבה churvah because a חורבה churvah doesn't actively
have people living there. If you were actively living there, right, then
you would be a problem of different ownership. But because it's a
vacant lot, you don't have the problem of conflicting ownership, but therefore
the only problem you have isn't the conflicting ownership isn't an issue.
The problem that you have is, is it too big of a
difference and is that considered therefore a problem according to the חכמים?
Chachamim? So let's see what... and רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon would say...
let's not worry about רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. Let's get through this.
So it says like this: Okay, so it says, אמר רב כהנא,
Amar Rav Kahana, לאו היינו דרמי בר חמא? Lav haynu de-Rami bar
Chama? Well, it's essentially רמי בר חמא's Rami bar Chama question about
the roof of an אכסדרה. achsadra. You know, more or less it's
the same question. So the גמרא Gemara says, so אמר רב ביבי
בר אביי Amar Rav Bibi bar Abaye or רב ביבי בר אביי
Rav Bibi bar Abaye said back to him who said, you know,
what type of question was that? We've just had a similar one.
So רב ביבי בר אביי Rav Bibi bar Abaye said, דכי מאחר
עצי ומתנצאי? De-khi me-acher atzei u-mitnatzei? What, am I taking my questions
from somebody else and coming to try to
make, make problems? Which is a little bit of a front, it's
some type of an idiom. idiomatic expression, but you know basically the
way רש"י Rashi says is, what do you think I'm doing? You
think I'm stealing somebody else's somebody else's, you think I'm stealing somebody
else's questions
and just coming to like show off or to make problems? I've
got my own question, you know, don't dismiss it saying it's somebody
else's, someone else already asked it. אכסדרא לא חזיא לדירה חורבא חזיא
לדירה. Achsadra lo chazya ledira, churva chazya ledira. There's a difference, okay?
So אכסדרא, achsadra, people don't usually live in it, or not, you
know, not at all, it's totally like, you know, just like a
nice little portico, whereas a חורבא churva is more fit in theory
if you wanted to to live in it. And therefore how how
should that translate? So the גמרא Gemara says השתא דחזיא לדירה מאי
קמיבעיא ליה? Hashta dechazya ledira mai kamibaya lei? So therefore, you know,
what exactly is his question related to the חורבא? churva? אם תמצי
לומר, Im timtzei lomar, he's saying if you if you say one
answer by the אכסדרא, achsadra, here's my question by the חורבא. churva.
אם תמצי לומר אכסדרא לא חזיא לדירה, Im timtzei lomar achsadra lo
chazya ledira, if you say that the אכסדרא achsadra is not fit
for living, and therefore what? So, hold on just one second.
If you say that it's permissible, meaning, you know, if you say
that the אכסדרא achsadra was okay, remember the only reason to say
that the אכסדרא achsadra was no good was because it's too similar,
it's like a גזירה, gezeira, it's too similar to another rooftop. But
in principle this should have been good. Why should it have been
good? Number one, it's a כרמלית, karmelit, okay? Number two, it's not
a distinct dwelling place, you know, like it's not considered to have
distinct ownership because nobody actually lives there, right? So A, nobody actually
lives there, the ownership is sort of like no one, okay? And
it's also a כרמלית, karmelit, so it should be similar enough, you
should be allowed to do it. So he says, if you say
that's okay because the ownership isn't really distinct, it's not necessarily the
same about a חורבא, churva, because a חורבא, churva, at least in
theory, this is more fit to be owned and, you know, maybe
it actually is even owned by somebody but they're an absentee landlord.
So therefore here, you know, maybe this is even if that's okay,
this is more problematic because that is more like a distinct ownership.
It only has two walls, how's it חזיא לדירה? chazya ledira? No,
it has three walls.
It's against the wall.
Okay, so anyway the גמרא Gemara says like this. חורבא, Churva, so
he says, do we say אם תמצי לומר אכסדרא לא חזיא לדירה
Im timtzei lomar achsadra lo chazya ledira and
therefore it's okay because it's not a distinct ownership, חורבא חזיא לדירה,
churva chazya ledira, the
חורבא churva is in theory could be inhabited even though the owner
is absentee, but that's enough to make it distinct. או דילמא השתא
מיהא לית בה דיורין? O dilma hashta miha leit bah diyurin?
Or do we say, okay, but right now nobody is living in
it, so it's not really a distinct domain, which is you know
an issue we had before about people that aren't at home on
שבת Shabbat and their effect on the courtyard? And therefore maybe it
should be okay? So the גמרא Gemara says תיקו, teiku, we don't
know the answer. Now I gotta tell you that again, what's implicit
and this is what is surprising and we will actually see this
in the גמרא, Gemara, what's implicit, this is why I told you
I wanted to say you were talking about a rooftop over the
courtyard, over the lot, because otherwise why is the גמרא Gemara only
bothered by the idea as is it distinct in terms of ownership?
It's a huge difference from going to the roof to the yard.
So the גמרא Gemara seems to assume and we're actually going to
see this later, that, I know this is a little bit I
know I was confusing you before but I have no choice here,
that this is actually the difference, right? רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says
כל גגות kol gagot are one domain, right? One domain, which means
that if you've got this scenario of,
and this is to חכמים, Chachamim, right? And the חכמים Chachamim say,
say
each גג gag is
different. Okay, each גג gag is different, right? That's the basic way
of רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir and the חכמים. Chachamim. So you have
the following two scenarios. You have a גג gag and a גג
gag with different ownerships, right? A and B, right? And that רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir says that's fine and the חכמים Chachamim say it's
no good. So the חכמים Chachamim are focusing on the ownership and
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir is focusing on the גג. gag. You could
have another scenario, right, which is a case of like a גג
gag and a חצר, chatzer, which is,
you know, owned by the same person, it's not an interesting case.
Of course you can take from one of your domains to your
other, okay, but owned by let's say by one person and let's
say I don't know, nobody lives here, okay, or whatever. It's hard
that nobody lives in a חצר, chatzer, so that would be something
like a חורבא. churva. So that's actually the mirror image of that
case. Is it, is the fact, is all that the חכמים Chachamim
care about different ownership? And maybe they would say that's okay, and
maybe, right, and maybe all that רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir cares about
is the similarity of the, you know, of the structure? So therefore
going from a גג gag to a חצר, chatzer, right, even if
it actually is not a problem of different ownership, right, maybe he
would actually say that's no good. Okay, so these, it's possible that
they would reverse their positions and not necessarily that he's always more
lenient and they're more strict. It might be they're looking at different
things. So the This case right here basically assumed that according to
the חכמים, Chachamim, going from a גג gag to a yard is
not inherently a problem. The only issue that the גמרא Gemara wants
to know is, is the fact that this is maybe a different
type of ownership, is that enough to create that problem like going
from roof to roof when there's a different ownership? Okay? But the
חכמים Chachamim are focusing on different ownership, whereas רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
is focusing on the difference between on the similarity of גג gag
and maybe for him a גג חצר gag chatzer or גג חורבה
gag churba distinction is a bigger issue. Yes? Since he looks at
it
as לא חזי לדירה, lo chazi ledira, I assume it's different. Like
in the past we've been pretty liberal about defining what constitutes חזי
לדירה, chazi ledira, right? And this seems to be the counterpoint in
some sense is it not, is it's adjacent
to the house, it's used by people.
Right. Well, but here we're trying to be lenient by saying לא
חזי לדירה lo chazi ledira you're making it a non-competing with the
rooftop. So it's a leniency here. Right? I mean, I agree that
it's inconsistent, you mean, you might be right. But it's basically a
leniency.
I thought you were going to say the other thing, that since
we say that by making an עירוב, eruv, if a guy is
visiting out of house visiting his daughter or something like that, that's
considered okay and he doesn't make a problem. So here, why do
we say that for the absentee landlord maybe he does make a
problem? Like in a way there's a possibility this is even stricter.
But again, you could argue that in the other case, in the
first case, everybody made an עירוב. eruv. You actively made an עירוב.
eruv. So how much is your non-participating when you're away from home
going to destroy that? Whereas here nobody made an עירוב eruv and
we're still trying to give you some latitude, some maybe here we
have higher demands to before we're able to consider it one space
even without an עירוב. eruv. Yes? So this whole question, who are
we actually asking it on, right? We're actually asking it within the
context of רב's Rav explanation of the חכמים. Chachamim. So you can't
carry ארבע אמות arba amot in your roof, but can you step
over, can you go over actually from one to the next? So
aren't we making it a more general question both on רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir and חכמים? Chachamim? You could and the גמרא Gemara is
going to get on with those types of questions. Okay? So again,
it's funny that the גמרא Gemara focuses on particular interpretations within one.
Some of these huge רש"י's Rashi are working out what would be
the implications for all the other variations, all the other תנאים Tannaim
and all the other reads of the אמוראים Amora'im in the תנאים
Tannaim and whatever. Yeah, that's what I was thinking about, that רש"י
Rashi there. I understand, well we haven't gotten to רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon yet. Okay? But anyway, look, that's what these huge רש"י's Rashi
try to work it all out. We got enough problems just following
what the גמרא Gemara is doing. Let's keep on going. Okay, so
the גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay, גגין השוין gagin hashavin ל
le רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir וגג יחידי vegag yachidi ל le רבנן.
Rabbanan. Now, now we're going to introduce a new debate. You've got,
okay, remember this case here was a מחלוקת machlokes רב ושמואל Rav
u-Shmuel because you cannot go from A to B does that make
A itself forbidden? Right? That was the big מחלוקת machlokes רב ושמואל.
Rav u-Shmuel. Now that was according to the חכמים. Chachamim.
Now what we want to say is according to רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon or רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir where all of the גגות gagos
are one.
So all of these according to רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir and it
could be a huge amount, right, and it could be in multiple
directions, all of these, the different ownership doesn't matter and they're all
one big space and you can carry from one to the next
because it's all גג גג גג, gag gag gag, right? What? And
the... well they have virtual walls because of the walls below. Okay?
So they're all one big space. So, one minute, let's take a
look.
So, גגין השוין gagin hashavin ל le רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, all
the גגות gagos that are on an equal plane, right, because
according to him if one is too high or too low it's
not part of the group. Or גג יחידי vegag yachidi ל le
רבנן, Rabbanan, and according to the rabbis you've just got your single
building. Single building they have no problem with. There's nobody it's competing
with, right, everybody of course says you can carry on that single
building. So you just say fine, everybody agrees all one domain, it's
got walls, carry on it and end of story. What type of
מחלוקת machlokes could there be? Well, let's take a look. Right? So
רב אמר מותר לטלטל בכולו, Rav amar mutar letaltel bekulo, you can
carry on either the standalone building or you can certainly or on
the connected
buildings according to רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir that it's all one domain.
מותר לטלטל בכולו. mutar letaltel bekulo. ושמואל אמר אין מטלטלין בו אלא
בארבע. u-Shmuel amar ein metaltelin bo ela be-arba. You can only carry
ארבע אמות, arba amot, which is like crazy. What? What? שמואל's Shmuel
the one that said that when you had competing גג gag A
and גג gag B, in each individual one you could carry fully.
Here, it's according to רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir who said you can
go from one to the next and he says you're limited to
ארבע אמות arba amot so you can like step over but you
can't go more than ארבע אמות? arba amot? What type of craziness
is that? So let's take a look at how the גמרא Gemara
explains it. So the גמרא Gemara says like this. So first it
asks the softball question. So רב אמר מותר לטלטל בכולו, Rav amar
mutar letaltel bekulo, you can go from one roof to the next.
קשיא דרב אדרב. kashya de-Rav a-de-Rav. What about the fact that רב
Rav said according to רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, I'm not רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir the חכמים, Chachamim, because when it was A against B
and so on and we looked at the גגות gagos as different,
you couldn't go even more than ארבע אמות? arba amot? How come
here he gives you all this latitude? So the answer is obvious.
התם לא מינכרא מחיצתא הכא מינכרא מחיצתא. hatam lo minkara mechitza hacha
minkara mechitza. Well actually the גמרא Gemara according to the רש"י Rashi
reads it that that was obvious, meaning... We don't look at them
as distinct, fine, you can go from one to the next. But
here's what the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* understands the question is. How come
says רש"י Rashi *Rashi*, the fact is that down here on the
street you might have like a רשות הרבים reshut harabim? *Reshus HaRabim*
on the street. Okay, so the question רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says is
why if רב Rav *Rav* when you had the case, right, when
you had the case of A and B, right, A and B,
רב Rav. *Rav* says you can't carry in A, even you can't
even carry in A. Why? Because he did not like the invisible
מחיצה mechitzah *mechitza*. Remember that was the debate of רב Rav, *Rav*
and שמואל Shmuel's *Shmuel*. Can you at least carry in A? And
רב Rav *Rav* says no, it's not an obvious enough מחיצה mechitzah?
*mechitza* to distinguish them and it's exposed completely to B.
So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says,
well how come here he says, you know, the people in the
רשות הרבים reshut harabim, *Reshus HaRabim*, right, this is exposed to the
רשות הרבים *Reshus HaRabim*. You said, you said A was exposed to
B, this is exposed to the רשות הרבים *Reshus HaRabim*, so that
should be like a כרמלית Carmelus. *karmelis*. If you have a רשות
היחיד reshut hayachid *Reshus HaYachid* completely open to a רשות הרבים *Reshus
HaRabim*, it loses its רשות היחיד reshus hayachid? *Reshus HaYachid* status. Okay,
so you know, you can, so this is exposed. It's not like
people inside the house they're protected, the rooftop is exposed. So why
isn't it like A being exposed to B? You're exposed to a
מקום אסור לו *makom assur lo*. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says
no, no, no, there's an obvious answer. The obvious answer is for
the people down here, they see the wall. Right, so when you
were on the top, the wall between A and B wasn't visible,
okay, and therefore created a problem for the חכמים Chachamim, *Chachamim*. But
here, from the people down here, the wall is visible and therefore
the roofs remain a distinct entity. All right, that was an easy
question, we wouldn't have even thought of the question, okay, let alone—so
that's רב Rav *Rav*. So רב Rav *Rav* says according to רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir, *Rabbi Meir* it's all one and you're fine. But
let's now try to understand שמואל Shmuel's *Shmuel* which really doesn't make
sense. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says קשיא דשמואל לשמואל *kashya deShmuel
leShmuel*. שמואל Shmuel: *Shmuel* who's lenient in the case of the חכמים
Chachamim's *Chachamim* says you can carry on all of A. Why here
all of a sudden when things should be better does he say
you can't carry? So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says התם לא הויא
יותר מבית סאתיים yoser mi-beis sa'atayim, הכא הויא יותר מבית סאתיים yoser
mi-beis sa'atayim. *hasam lo havya yoser mi-bais sasayim hacha havya yoser mi-bais
sasayim*. So what שמואל Shmuel *Shmuel* is saying is I'm not saying
in general you can't go from one rooftop to the next. Of
course you can, that's what the משנה Mishnah *mishnah* says. The משנה
*mishnah* says according to רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir, *Rabbi Meir* it's כולו
רשות אחת *kulu reshus achas*, of course you can travel from one
roof to the next. But what about the following scenario? What about
what happens is when you combine all of the rooftops it's—it becomes
more than one בית סאתיים beis sa'atayim, *bais sasayim*. Now this becomes
more of a problem for רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir *Rabbi Meir* than
the חכמים chachamim, *Chachamim*. The חכמים *Chachamim* say each building is distinct,
so therefore we never look at it as one big unit, it
never becomes בית סאתיים beis sa'atayim *bais sasayim* and therefore at least
you can carry on A because it's distinct from B. Okay, but
according—you can't go from A to B according to the חכמים *Chachamim*
but you can carry on A. But according to רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir *Rabbi Meir* that says it's all one, all one is great
while it's less than בית סאתיים beis sa'atayim *bais sasayim*. But as
soon as by combining all of them it's more than בית סאתיים
beis sa'atayim. *bais sasayim* and he says it's all one, now you've
got a כרמלית karmelit, *karmelis*. It's more than בית סאתיים beis sa'atayim
*bais sasayim*, it's not surrounded by walls for the sake of habitation.
The walls down here are to inhabit the building, not to inhabit
the roof. So it's more than בית סאתיים beis sa'atayim *bais sasayim*,
not הוקף לדירה hukaf ledira. *hukaf ledira* and that becomes a כרמלית
karmelis. *karmelis*. But right, according—so basically now the debate of רב Rav
*Rav* and שמואל Shmuel, *Shmuel* here is because the way the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* continues it sounds like רב Rav *Rav* doesn't disagree in
principle that you're right, according to רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir *Rabbi Meir*
these all combine as one big thing and you would look at
it as one big בית סאתיים beit satayim, *bais sasayim*. But רב
Rav *Rav*'s difference is that he says the walls you make down
here for living in the building make the roof also considered הוקף
לדירה hukaf ledira? *hukaf ledira*. They're the same wall so since they're
הוקף לדירה hukaf ledira *hukaf ledira* for the inside of the house
they make the rooftop הוקף לדירה hukaf ledira. *hukaf ledira* as well.
Okay, so let's see as the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* continues. I have
a question. Yeah. If they designate this whole thing a כרמלית karmelis.
*karmelis*, that negates the fact that it is a רשות היחיד reshus
hayachid *Reshus HaYachid*. Right, because even if you have a כרמלית karmelis
*karmelis* that's more than בית סאתיים beit satayim, *bais sasayim* that's not
surrounded for דירה dirah. *dira*, it stops being a—I mean דאורייתא *de-oraisa*
it's רשות היחיד reshus hayachid, *Reshus HaYachid* but rabbinically you can't carry
on it. Which I don't know if Rabbi Jachter mentioned this
yesterday on the field trip, but this is one of the biggest
problems with an עירוב *eruv*. If you make the עירוב *eruv*
around the whole city and then right in the middle you've got
a lake, okay, and a lake is more than בית סאתיים *bais
sasayim*, it's not הוקף לדירה hukaf ledira *hukaf ledira* because in the
sense that people can't live on the lake, and then so okay
fine I won't carry on the lake. But no, but then what
do you say about the rest of everything else? It's פרוץ במילואו
למקום אסור לו *parutz bimlo'o le-makom assur lo*, because all the rest
of the רשות היחיד reshus hayachid. *Reshus HaYachid* is fully exposed to
the lake which is אסור *assur*, which is a כרמלית karmelis *karmelis*.
So any עירוב *eruv* cannot contain any space within the עירוב *eruv*
of יותר מבית סאתיים yoser mi-beis sa'atayim. *yoser mi-bais sasayim* not fit
for habitation. So we wind up coming up with a lot of
קולות *kulas* of what defines הוקף לדירה hukaf ledira, *hukaf ledira*, like
you know the fact that sometimes people float toy boats at the
edge of the lake makes the whole lake הוקף לדירה hukaf ledira
*hukaf ledira* because people use it, okay, or things like that. Anyway
let's continue. The גמרא Gemara says: התם לא הוי יותר מבית סאתיים,
hasam lo havei yoser mi-beis sa'atayim, הכא הוי יותר מבית סאתיים, hacha
havei yoser mi-beis sa'atayim, והני מחיצות למטה עבידן, ve-hani mechitsos lemata avidun,
and the walls are made for the inside the house. למעלה לא
עבידן, lemala lo avidun, and are not made for the roof. והוי
ככרפף יותר מבית סאתיים, ve-havei ke-karfap yoser mi-beis sa'atayim, it's like an
open field more than בית סאתיים, which is five thousand square אמות,
amos, שלא הוקף לדירה, shelo hukaf ledira, that was not surrounded for
the, you know, walled in for the sake of habitation. וכל כרפף
יותר מבית סאתיים שלא הוקף לדירה אין מטלטלין בו אלא בארבע. ve-chol
karfap yoser mi-beis sa'atayim shelo hukaf ledira ein metaltelin bo ela be-arba.
Then it becomes like a כרמלית. karmelis. And again, based on the
continued גמרא, Gemara the גמרא Gemara is going to say that רבא
Rava agrees in principle that according to רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir they
all become one unit and all becomes בית סאתיים or יותר מבית
סאתיים, yoter m'beit satayim. but רבא Rava would just say the walls
below make the space on top הוקף לדירה. hukaf l'dirah, Now the
גמרא Gemara has like this: ספינה. sfina. So now we're moving on
to another question. You got a boat. Okay, what's the story about
carrying on the boat? Because you got the walls of the boat.
So רבא Rava says: מותר לטלטל בכולה, mutar le-taltel be-kula, you can
carry in the boat. That's a good thing. ושמואל ve-Shmuel says: אין
מטלטלין בו אלא בארבע. ein metaltelin bo ela be-arba. Same thing, you
can't carry in the boat. Why? Because the boat is, let's assume,
יותר מבית סאתיים. yoter m'beit satayim. You've got a big boat, right?
You don't have to be that big to be יותר מבית סאתיים.
So are the walls of the boat going to make the top,
make the deck, הוקף לדירה? hukaf l'dirah, It's just like the house
and the roof. The walls of the boat and the deck, do
they make it הוקף לדירה hukaf l'dirah or not? So רבא, Rava,
let's take a look. רבא, Rava, because you said, yeah, of course
people actually live on the deck regularly, but what is the primary
purpose of making the walls of a boat? So רבא Rava says:
מותר לטלטל בכולה, mutar le-taltel be-kula, דהא איכא מחיצה. de-ha ika mechitsa.
You've got the walls and therefore it's הוקף, hukaf, and it's הוקף
לדירה. hukaf ledira, ושמואל ve-Shmuel says: אין מטלטלין בו אלא בארבע אמות.
ein metaltelin bo ela be-arba amos. מחיצות לאברוחי מיא עבידן. mechitsos le-avruchi
maya avidun. The reason, first reason you make the walls on a
boat is so that it won't take on water and that it'll
float. Okay, so it's not like, oh, they're going to be people
living here, we've got to make walls. No, you've got to make
walls if you want some type of structure that's going to actually
float on water. So therefore, he would actually say it again becomes
a יותר מבית סאתיים שלא הוקף לדירה. yoser mi-beis sa'atayim shelo hukaf
ledira. He might even say it interestingly for the space on the,
in the hull of the boat, right? That maybe he really considers
the walls not at all made to create a livable space on
the inside. Even though you sleep inside? I know, it's a little
crazy. I don't know, it's not clear if he's talking about the
deck or the hull, but if it's the hull and you actually
made rooms, then the walls you would make for the individual rooms
would be הוקף לדירה hukaf ledira, and also it wouldn't be an
open space. But let's say, you know, like those galley boats, right,
where they would have the slaves, you know, doing their thing and
you had a really a בית סאתיים there with no individual rooms,
right, is that considered to be הוקף לדירה, hukaf ledira that open
space in the hull? It's actually the bottom of the house. It's,
yes, because clearly it serves that function too and it's intended even
if it's not the first and the primary. I totally agree. I
don't even see how you could say it's not the primary. I
mean, the reason that you want to keep the water out of
the boat is so that you'll have a boat that you can
inhabit. But not necessarily to create a place of habitation. I mean,
you know, I mean it depends, I guess, what you call לדירה
ledira means. Like even if it were a cargo boat, is using
a space for carrying cargo הוקף לדירה hukaf ledira or not? You
know, it's for human use and facility. I know, because it's manned.
I don't know, it's very hard to understand שמואל's Shmuel position, I
agree. Otherwise you wouldn't be on it. What? On שבת. Shabbos. Not
necessarily. You could start on the trip. A galley boat, a galley
boat, who would be on it on שבת? Shabbos? Maybe nowadays we
wouldn't, who knows? You know, you go on a trip and you
have to, so you took a בית סאתיים. How much it is?
It's not very much at all. So anyway, what? בית סאתיים is
about, is about a hundred feet by a hundred feet. That's what
a בית סאתיים is, okay? That's not, that's not, that's not very
much at all. Ships are much larger. Okay, we have that whole
thing with רבן גמליאל, Rabban Gamliel, remember? I know, people would be
on boats. They wouldn't start on שבת, Shabbos, but they'd be there
on שבת, Shabbos, yes. But typical Mediterranean galleys of that time were
not that large. Right, oh, okay, even as recently as five hundred
years ago, ships, ocean-going ships were really tiny. Okay, so this would
not be an issue. Okay, good, okay. But if it would come
up, anyway, it's the same debate, although שמואל's Shmuel position is starting
to become a lot harder to understand. Okay, let's focus. מחיצות לאברוחי
מיא עבידן. mechitsos le-avruchi maya avidun. אמר ליה רב חייה בר יוסף
לשמואל. amar lei Rav Chiya bar Yosef le-Shmuel. So רב חייה בר
יוסף Rav Chiya bar Yosef said to שמואל: Shmuel. הלכתא כוותך או
הלכתא כרבא? hilchosa kevassach o hilchosa ke-Rava? How do we rule? אמר
ליה הלכתא כרבא. amar lei hilchosa ke-Rava. It's okay, don't worry, it's
like רבא. Rava. So first of all, I love this because this
basically says that you can believe in your position but not insist,
you know, that we פסק pasken this way. You accept the fact
that the accepted פסק psak is like the other position. Okay, and
even when you are asked, meaning it's not, you know, you're not
going to try to say: Oh, you're asking me, I'm going to
tell you to listen to me. You actually are willing to endorse
what is the accepted פסק. psak. Okay, אמר רב גידל אמר רב
חייה בר יוסף, amar Rav Gidal amar Rav Chiya bar Yosef, ומודה
רבא, u-modeh Rava, רבא Rava would agree, אם כפה פיה, im kapa
pi-ha, if you turned the boat upside down, שאין מטלטלין בו אלא
בארבע אמות, she-ein metaltelin bo ela be-arba amos, then, and you wanted
to sort of live in the hull of the boat, that, you
know, that you could only carry four אמות. amos. Anyway, and you
want to live inside of the boat, and there he says, there
he'll agree that that's not הוקף לדירה, hukaf ledira, again assuming it's
יותר מבית סאתיים. So the question is: why not? So let's take
a look. So the גמרא Gemara says like this: כפה למה? kafa
l'mah? Why are you turning it upside down? אילימא לדור תחתיה, Ilima
l'dor tachteha, because you actually plan on, you know, sheltering yourself in
it, so מאי שנא מגג יחידי? mai shna migag yechidi? Why is
it different than, you know, just an individual rooftop? רב Rav said
in an individual rooftop, even if it was bigger than בית סאתיים,
it's considered הוקף לדירה, hukaf ledira and here even more so. You
actually made the walls when you turned it upside down. You effectively
made walls so you could live in it. What better הוקף לדירה
hukaf ledira do you need than that? אלא שכפאה לזופתה. Ela she'kfaha
l'zufta. You're turning it upside down because you're doing repairs, you're putting,
you're putting tar on it. So therefore in that case, he said,
now I've turned it upside down, and this guy out here is
doing repairs on it, okay? Here's his, here's his paintbrush or whatever.
He's doing repairs on it. Okay, so in that case, these walls
are not made לדירה. l'dirah. They were created by flipping over the
boat and essentially created a new reality of walls, and those were
not created to make that as a habitable space. When you're making
a boat, he says, you know, your normal, it's a normal configuration,
then he says like we've all been saying, he says, yeah, you
do it for the water, but you've done it so people can
live in it. But essentially this is considered like, this is considered
like making it new and creating a new space, because the livable
space over here is this, right? That's the livable space. Here, the
livable space is not the bottom, it's the, you know, you've reversed
what the livable space is. So he says, here you've created new
walls and you're not making them לדירה, l'dirah, and therefore that case
I would agree. This idea, by the way, just reminds me, you
know, this idea, well, you created the walls new, it's the same
boat. There is, רב משה Rav Moshe was asked about, you know,
do you have to be טובל? tovel? Oh, because he got a
כלי kli here. Do you have to be טובל? tovel? Like if
you take a jar, a disposable jar, you know, things that, and
you want to then save it and use it, do you have
to be טובל tovel it? So רב משה Rav Moshe said, you
know, so he said you can use it, you know, before you've
decided to save it because it's disposable, it's not really a כלי
kli or whatever. But now you're going to want to keep it
and use it, do you have to be טובל tovel it? So
רב משה Rav Moshe says no, because the moment you decide to
keep it and not throw it out, you've made it into a
כלי. kli. So now it's like a כלי kli made by a
יהודי, Yehudi, and a כלי kli made by a יהודי Yehudi doesn't
have to have טבילה. tevilah. So anyway, so... what about like those
disposable like aluminum pans? I am not going further with that story.
Let's keep going. So the גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay, רב
אשי מתני לה אספינה. Rav Ashi matni lah asfina. So רב אשי
Rav Ashi had that this discussion, when he said רב אשי Rav
Ashi says this is the question of when he said הלכתא כמאן,
hilchata k'man, so you know, who do we go like, that that
was relating to the case of the boat, because we said, you
know, that that was a debate and then it was asked how
do we rule? And שמואל Shmuel, said we rule like רב. Rav
רב אחא בריה דרבא מתני לה אאכסדרא. Rav Acha brei d'Rava matni
lah a'achsadra. And רב אחא בריה דרבא Rav Acha brei d'Rava said
that that question to שמואל, Shmuel who do we rule like, and
שמואל Shmuel said we rule like רב, was not relating to this
immediate discussion about a boat, it was relating to another debate of
רב and שמואל Shmuel about a portico. What was that debate? דאיתמר,
D'itmar, it was taught: אכסדרא בבקעה. Achsadra b'vikah. You have a portico
in a valley. רב אמר מותר לטלטל בכולה, Rav amar mutar l'taltel
bekula, you can carry in it. ושמואל אמר אין מטלטין בה אלא
בארבע. U'Shmuel amar ein mtaltelin bah ela b'arba. Okay, now this is
not about a huge space and a, and a what do you
call it, and a בית סאתיים, יותר מבית סאתיים. This is a
small portico and you want to carry underneath it. What should be
the problem? So the question is: where are the walls? So רב
אמר מותר לטלטל בכולה, Rav amar mutar l'taltel bekula, you can carry
in it. אמרינן פי תקרה יורד וסותם. Amrinan pi tikra yored v'sotem.
We say the edge of the roof goes down and seals, it
creates virtual walls. ושמואל אמר אין מטלטין בה אלא בארבע, U'Shmuel amar
ein mtaltelin bah ela b'arba, you can only, it's a כרמלית, you
only can carry within four אמות. amot. לא אמרינן פי תקרה יורד
וסותם. La amrinan pi tikra yored v'sotem. You do not say that
the edge goes down. So this is a completely different debate, okay?
And this comes up in the גמרא Gemara in סוכה Sukkah quotes
it as well. And this is really a question of what are
the parameters of פי תקרה יורד וסותם. pi tikra yored v'sotem. You've
got an אכסדרא achsadra which has these things, it does not have
walls, it has, you know, whatever, the posts, okay? And it's in
a valley, so there's no houses near it, nothing else can count
as walls. Can this count as walls? These are more than three
טפחים tfachim away from one another, the pillars. Okay, so the point
is: can you use the edge of the, of the roof, right,
because it's got a little thickness going down in the vertical, can
you imagine that as a virtual wall and say that it goes
down and פי תקרה יורד וסותם? pi tikra yored v'sotem? Okay, and
that's the debate. Now רש״י Rashi says, because it's interesting because normally
often we do say פי תקרה יורד וסותם. pi tikra yored v'sotem.
So רש״י Rashi says what makes this case distinct is that you
want to say it on all four sides. You're not just doing
it to seal off one wall, you want to make four virtual
walls. תוספות Tosafot says that no, the debate is even just for
one wall, רב and שמואל. Shmuel debating פי תקרה יורד וסותם. pi
tikrah yored vesotem. I want to remind you about the irony of
the law פי תקרה יורד וסותם. pi tikrah yored vesotem. If you
have a straight מחיצה that's suspended off of the ground, מחיצה תלויה,
mechitzah tluyah, whatever, something like this, right, we say that if it's
more than three טפחים, tfachim, it can't go down because because the
little goats go through it. Okay, whatever. Anyway, okay, but here if
the beginning of the going down maybe it's just one טפח, tefach,
it's not this is ten טפחים tfachim and it's no good, but
this is just maybe one טפח tefach but because it's connected to
it's part of a roof and the idea of a roof maybe
creates more of the sense of a domicile and a house implicitly,
so using the edge of a roof to go down, that you
might be able to do, while whereas you can't do that. And
that's the debate of רב and שמואל, Shmuel would we say פי
תקרה יורד וסותם, pi tikrah yored vesotem, completely unrelated to all the
discussions before, a straight question of what constitutes a מחיצה? All right,
so let's now go, now the גמרא Gemara, turns to back to
the positions of the תנאים Tannaim and back to some of the
discussion from before, but I really want to get to the bottom
of the דף, daf, so let's take a look. Okay, ורב אליבא
דרבי מאיר לטלטולי מגג לחצר, veRav aliba deRabbi Meir letaltuli migag lechatzer,
so now the גמרא Gemara says like this, רב according to רבי
מאיר, Rabbi Meir right, רבי מאיר who says that basically, let me
draw this again, go back to you have all of your roofs,
right, all of your connected roofs, right, and basically according to רבי
מאיר they're all one big thing, it's all one גג. gag. Okay,
and רב says what? רב says not only is it one גג,
gag, הוקף לדירה, hukaf ledira, right, that the walls, everybody agrees the
walls extend, but רב say because down here it's הוקף לדירה, hukaf
ledira it's like it's הוקף לדירה hukaf l'dira? up here. Okay, so
now the גמרא Gemara wants to say the following, I erased that
chart, I should have remembered רבי מאיר says if you have גג
gag and גג, gag, okay, even though they're owned by different people,
that's okay because they're all because they are all the same גג.
gag. What if you have גג gag and חצר, chatzer, right, even
if somehow they're non-competing? Is the fact that there's a difference between
גג gag and חצר chatzer a problem? And the גמרא Gemara actually
is going to say, like I told you before, that for רבי
מאיר this difference is a problem and you can't do that. So
now the גמרא Gemara wants to know why is that? If רב
considers this space הוקף לדירה hukaf l'dira. and the חצר chatzer is
also, like there's walls around a חצר, chatzer, it's הוקף לדירה, hukaf
l'dira, think about the similar qualities: הוקף לדירה and the people generally
use it, but the actual like living is, you know, periodic, right?
People don't really live in it. Okay, and the same about a
חצר, chatzer, it's הוקף לדירה but it's not a prime maybe the
better way to saying it's not primary, it's not a primary דירה.
And that's true here too, not primary. So even though one is,
you know, a structure and high and the other is low and
on the ground, but why do you think גג gag and חצר
chatzer are dissimilar? You know, you call that הוקף לדירה, it's not
a primary place to live like a house, this is also הוקף
לדירה not a primary place to live. So why not go from
a גג gag to a חצר? chatzer? So the גמרא Gemara says
like this, ורב אליבא דרבי מאיר לטלטולי מגג לחצר גזירה משום דרבי
יצחק בר אבדימי. veRav aliba deRabbi Meir letaltuli migag lechatzer gezeira mishum
deRabbi Yitzchak bar Avdimi. No, remember what we said two or three
days ago? דרבי יצחק בר אבדימי deRabbi Yitzchak bar Avdimi about going
on from רשות היחיד reshus hayachid to a pillar and that you'll
confuse it with a pillar in the middle of a רשות הרבים?
So the basic answer is, to reframe it is, you might be
right that abstract qualities are the same, but physically a גג gag
is much different than a חצר. chatzer. This is high up and
that's low down and the גמרא Gemara frames it as a גזירה
gezeira you'll come to putting things on pillars in a רשות הרבים,
but the simple way I would just say it is that גג
gag and חצר chatzer are very physically different types of things and
therefore that's enough of a difference and you can't go from one
to the other. Now the גמרא says like this, ושמואל אליבא דרבנן
לטלטולי מגג לקרפף, veShmuel aliba deRabbanan letaltuli migag lekarpaf, and שמואל Shmuel
according to the רבנן, Rabbanan, שמואל says that this is considered לא
הוקף לדירה, lo hukaf ledira, right? Right? שמואל says that this is,
right, לא הוקף לדירה, lo hukaf ledira, yes? So שמואל just said
that, it was לא הוקף לדירה, lo hukaf ledira, okay. So then
the question is like this, now שמואל would say לא הוקף לדירה
lo hukaf ledira whether according to whether according to רבי מאיר or
the חכמים, he wouldn't make a distinction. But going back to the
חכמים position, where you have the sense of it being different and
שמואל says you can carry here, but nevertheless his basic position is
that that's considered to be לא הוקף לדירה. lo hukaf ledira. Well
you know what that should be similar to, says the גמרא, that
should be similar to a קרפף, karpaf, not a חצר, chatzer, but
whatever, if you have a קרפף, karpaf, right. Got like a yard,
a field, okay, what are the- which also has walls, like a
fenced-in field, what are the qualities, technically is a רשות היחיד? reshus
hayachid Yes. But is it הוקף לדירה? No. Basic קרפף karpaf is
לא הוקף לדירה. lo hukaf l'dira. That's what, what, that's the basic
assumption, okay? You maybe you have it there for your animals or
something, whatever it would be considered לא הוקף לדירה. lo hukaf l'dira.
So again, why can't you go from here to here? Okay, they
both share the qualities of being a real רשות היחיד and not
being הוקף לדירה. And we know that according to the חכמים, even
though we might say you can go from a גג gag to
a חצר, chatzer, they do not- they say you cannot go from
a גג gag to a קרפף. karpaf. Why not? Don't they share
the same qualities? Let's just read the answer. Okay? So the גמרא
says, אמר רבא בר עולא גזירה שמא יפחת הגג. Amar Rava bar
Ula gzeira shema yipaches hagag. Okay, so a very side reason. Okay,
again, according to me the answer could just be, you know, physically
they're different, but as we'll see, the גמרא tomorrow, well that's not
sufficient because it distinguishes between קרפף karpaf and חצר chatzer and so
on. So we do care about these qualities. So why isn't that
enough to say that you can go from one to the other?
So the answer is maybe the roof will become smaller. Now hold
on, what does that mean? Okay. Oh, I think I misstated this,
hold on one minute. Oh, I misstated, one minute. I'm sorry, I
misstated. רש"י says, this fits the answer, okay, תוספות Tosafos has a
very different read of the answer. רש"י says the case is we're
talking about, excuse me, is that it is a very large roof.
Okay, it's a very large roof, it's one single roof and it
is יותר מבית סאתים. yoser mibeis sa'atayim. So according to that it's
not a רשות היחיד, it's a כרמלית. And similarly the field we're
talking about is very large and therefore it's a כרמלית. So the
same question, except assuming more than בית סאתים. beis sa'atayim. So why
can't you carry from one כרמלית to the other? Okay, and they're
both לא הוקף לדירה lo hukaf l'dira and the answer is, yeah,
I don't know, maybe like there'll be a break in the roof
here or something like that, and then this will and they won't
fix it and this will become or you know, I don't know,
this this edge will fall down and this will become less than
בית סאתים. beis sa'atayim. And it'll turn into a רשות היחיד. And
then you'll wind up carrying from רשות היחיד to a כרמלית- well
the גמרא is going to say that. Okay, anyway, it's a very
strange answer and the גמרא's answer is אי הכי מקרפף לקרפף נמי
לא יטלטל דילמא מיפחת ואתי לטלטולי. ei hachi mikarpaf l'karpaf nami lo
yitaltel dilma mipachas v'asi l'taltuli. So okay, then don't carry from one
קרפף karpaf to the next, maybe one will somehow the walls will
move and it will become less than בית סאתים beis sa'atayim and
it'll be a רשות היחיד to a כרמלית. So the גמרא says
no. התם אי מיפחת מינכרא מילתא. hasam ei mipachas minkara milsa. There
if something happens it's obvious because you see the walls are surrounding
a different sized space. הכא אי מיפחת לא מינכרא מילתא. hacha ei
mipachas lo minkara milsa. Here if something happens it won't be as
obvious because here the walls are all invisible. So if something happened,
you know, it's not exactly בית סאתים, beis sa'atayim, you're aware that
something fell down over there. In your mind you assume it's still
בית סאתים, beis sa'atayim, but you don't- aren't able to estimate the
space well because it's not really surrounded by walls. So in a
place which is really surrounded by walls we're not afraid that the
configuration will change because you'll see a different type of space that's
surrounded. But here where the walls are invisible, we're concerned. Anyway, it's
a very, it's a very side answer, but what we are leading
up to is the discussion tomorrow which is today was the focus
on different ownerships creating a competition. Here we're going to talk about
different types of spaces and which is what the simpler sense of
the משנה was, going from one type of a space to the
other. And the גמרא's saying maybe we should define the similarity of
spaces, not just the physical reality, but these types of abstract things
like הוקף לדירה, primary residence, not primary residence and why do we
define certain things as a similar space and certain things as a
different space. So this will all be for tomorrow's דף. daf. I
know you are waiting with bated breath.